

Geneviève Verdier

Last Updated: May 10, 2019

Geneviève Verdier is a Deputy Division chief in the Fiscal Affairs Department of the IMF. She completed a PhD at the University of British Columbia. Her research interest include fiscal policy and digitalization, sovereign debt restructuring, economic growth, international macroeconomics and financial development. Prior to joining the Fund, she was an Assistant Professor at Texas A&M University. She has also worked as an economist at the Bank of Canada.

Email: gverdier@imf.org

Fluent In: French.

Education:

PhD Economics, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, Canada, 2004

MA, Economics, Queen's University, Kingston, Canada, 1996

BA Honours, Economics and Finance, McGill University, Montreal, Canada, 1995

Previous Experience:

Senior Economist, Strategy, Policy and Review Department, International Monetary Fund

Senior Economist, African Department, International Monetary Fund, 2012-Present

Economist, African Department, International Monetary Fund, 2009-2011

Economist, IMF Institute, African Division, International Monetary Fund, 2006-2009

Assistant Professor, Department of Economics, Texas A&M University, 2003-2007

Economist, Bank of Canada, 1996-1998

Current Position:

Deputy Division Chief, Fiscal Affairs Department, IMF

Country work or Mission Assignment:

Ghana desk, African Department, IMF, 2011-Present

Zimbabwe desk, African Department, IMF, 2009-2011

Field of Expertise:

Public Finance

Open Economy Macroeconomics

Macro-Financial Issues

Development Economics

IMF Books and Working Papers:

From Ambition to Execution: Policies in Support of Sustainable Development Goals, Staff Discussion Notes No. 15/18, September 22, 2015

Building a Common Future in Southern Africa, April 05, 2013

The Design of Fiscal Adjustment Strategies in Botswana, Lesotho, Namibia, and Swaziland, Working Paper No. 11/266, November 01, 2011

Mother, Can I trust the Government?Sustained Financial Deepening - A Political InstitutionsView, Working Paper No. 10/210, September 01, 2010

FDI Flows to Low-Income Countries: Global Drivers and Growth Implications, Working Paper No. 10/132, June 01, 2010

Firm Productivity, Innovation and Financial Development, Working Paper No. 10/49, February 01, 2010

A Real Model of Transitional Growth and Competitiveness in China, Working Paper No. 08/99, April 01, 2008

Lucas vs. Lucas: On Inequality and Growth, Working Paper No. 07/17, January 01, 2007

IMF Occasional Papers, Pamphlets, and Special Issues Papers

"Digital Government", Capitalizing on Good Times, April 2018 Fiscal Monitor, Chapter 2.

Making Public Investment More Efficient

The Fund's Lending Framework and Sovereign Debt-Further Considerations

THE FUND'S LENDING FRAMEWORK AND SOVEREIGN DEBT-PRELIMINARY CONSIDERATIONS

THE FUND'S LENDING FRAMEWORK AND SOVEREIGN DEBT-ANNEXES

STRENGTHENING THE CONTRACTUAL FRAMEWORK TO ADDRESS COLLECTIVE ACTION PROBLEMS IN SOVEREIGN DEBT RESTRUCTURING

ENHANCING FINANCIAL SECTOR SURVEILLANCE IN LOW-INCOME COUNTRIES: FINANCIAL DEEPENING AND MACROSTABILITY

ENHANCING FINANCIAL SECTOR SURVEILLANCE IN LOW-INCOME COUNTRIES—BACKGROUND PAPER

iMFdirect Blog Posts

The Digital Gamble: New Technology Transforms Fiscal Policy, with V. Gaspar

F&D articles

"Public Finance Goes Digital" with S, Gupta, M. Keen and A. Shah, 2018.

"Trusting the Government" with M. Quintyn, 2010.

"The Domestic Solution" with L. Lipschitz and C. Rochon, 2009.

Other Published Materials

In the Wake of the Global Economic Crisis: Adjusting to Lower Revenues in Bostwana, Lesotho, amibia and Swaziland (with . Mongardini, . Bencio, T. Fontaine, Pastor), 2011.

Books

Digital Revolutions in Public Finance, with S. Gupta, M. Keen, A. Shah (eds), 2018.

"African Finance in the 21st Century" (Marc Quintyn and Genevieve Verdier, eds), 2010, Palgrave-MacMillan.

Building a Common Future in Southern Africa, 2013 (with J. Mongardini, A. Cuevas, T. Asonuma, . Basdevant, X. Debrun, . Engstrom, I. Vasquez, V. Kramarenko, L. Leigh, P. Masson), International Monetary Fund

Publications in Journals (Refereed)

Firm Productivity, Innovation and Financial Development, Southern Economic Journal, 79, 422-49 (with E. Kersting and E. Dabla-Norris)

"A Real Model of Transitional Growth and Competitiveness in China" (with L. Lipschitz and C. Rochon), Journal of Asian Economics, 22 (2011), 267-283.

"What Drives Long-Term Capital Flows: A Theoretical and Empirical Investigation", Journal of International Economics, 74 (2008), 120-142.

"Inequality and Growth: Some Welfare Calculations" (with Juan-Carlos Cordoba), Journal of Economic Dynamics and Control, 32 (2008), 1812-29.

"Measuring Internal Trade Distances: A New Method Applied to Estimate Provincial Border Effects in Canada" (with John Helliwell), Canadian Journal of Economics, 32 (2001), 1024-41.

"Structural Influences on Participation Rates: A Canada-U.S. Comparison" (with Irene Ip and Sheryl King), Canadian Business Economics, 7 (1999), 25-41.

Other Published Materials

Digital revolutions in public finance, with S. Gupta, M. Keen, A. Shah, VOX CEPR's Policy Portal, 2018.

Mother, Can I Trust the Government? Stable democracies are more likely to enjoy sustained financial development, with M. Quintyn, VOX CEPR's Policy Portal, 2010.